<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The third step of a nonconformist, for the recovery of the use of his ministry with some occasional notice taken of the judgment and decree of the University of Oxford, past in their convocation, July 21, 1683 / by one of the followers of peace, and lovers of impartiality.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18320559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18320559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1636:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The third step of a nonconformist, for the recovery of the use of his ministry with some occasional notice taken of the judgment and decree of the University of Oxford, past in their convocation, July 21, 1683 / by one of the followers of peace, and lovers of impartiality.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107352:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE THIRD STEP OF A Nonconformiſt, For Recovery of the Uſe of his Miniſtry. WITH Some Occaſional Notice taken of the Judgment and Decree of the <hi>Univerſity of Oxford,</hi> paſt in their Convocation, <hi>July</hi> 21. 1683.</p>
            <p>By one of the Followers of Peace, and Lovers of Impartiality.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Probitas laudatur &amp; alget.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ju.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns,</hi> the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1684.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107352:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107352:2"/>
            <head>The Third Step.</head>
            <p>THE Year <hi>Eighty Two</hi> preſenting ſome riſe to the Nonconformiſt for new thoughts about their returning into the Vineyard, upon the Expiration of one Clauſe in the <hi>Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> required by the <hi>Act for Uniformity,</hi> which was of deepeſt Reſentment to many, and the greateſt cauſe of their Ejection, it ſeemed reaſonable to me to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my ſelf to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs upon that Errand. It was not for any <hi>Preferment</hi> that I ſeek, (for I am not like to <hi>Conform</hi> ſo far) but it was for a <hi>Liberty</hi> only of <hi>Preaching</hi> without <hi>Moleſtation,</hi> as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Emolument,</hi> which is in effect for the licenſe only of exerciſing a piece of <hi>Self-denial,</hi> in coming out of a ſtate of <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>caſe,</hi> into a ſtate of <hi>work,</hi> of <hi>care,</hi> of <hi>cenſure,</hi> that if it ſo pleaſe God, I might yet be ſome way ſerviceable to my Generation, and my Old Age not altogether unprofitable. Unto this end I Printed lately four or five Sheets, entituling them, <hi>Two Steps in order hereunto,</hi> appointing my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107352:3"/>Bookſeller, as ſoon as they were done, to ſend them to the Biſhop and Archbiſhop, with a Letter from me to both, the Contents whereof were, humbly to crave their <hi>pardon</hi> for my ſending thoſe Sheets, and their <hi>leave</hi> to wait on them after due time of read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to know their pleaſure, ſignifying my unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs to ſurpriſe them, but that they might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider beforehand, and if it were good for them, to <hi>deny</hi> or <hi>grant</hi> my requeſt at <hi>firſt hearing,</hi> it would be good to do the ſame <hi>after deliberation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſtay'd ten days or thereabout, and then went my ſelf to both in perſon; I found no pride, and no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but all the civility, that becomes the gravity, candour, and dignity of ſuch perſons: but I found they had not read my Sheets, ſo as either to have underſtood what I ſought, or conſidered whether it could be granted. Upon this I ſpared not to write again to both, for the informing them in <hi>ſhort,</hi> and yet in <hi>full,</hi> what it was I deſired, and I went again al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to one of them, thinking to have ſpoke with him, but he ſent me back word, I muſt come another time, he was then buſie. Whether this Meſſage by his Servant did ſignifie his unwillingneſs to be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed any further, or that I ſhould indeed take a better opportunity when he had more leiſure, I am in doubt: but for the prevention of the fruſtrating an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of this kind (if it may be conſcionably effected)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107352:3"/>I do upon this further pauſe judge it expedient, (if not neceſſary) to add a <hi>Third</hi> Step to my <hi>Two</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, before I go to any Biſhop more in this matter. For having by my ſelf and friends made ſome tryal of the Inclinations of more than theſe two of them, I am induced to a recollection upon the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and to ſet my ſelf, if it be poſſible, to come yet to a cloſer point with them than I have already about the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is not (I know) for any Chriſtian to judge of anothers <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is know only to a man's own ſelf and God; and much leſs is he to make <hi>his</hi> Judgment the ſtandard or meaſure to <hi>another</hi> mans. <hi>Conſcience</hi> in this caſe is nothing elſe but the inward Judgment of a mans Soul, whether ſuch a thing be lawful for him to do in the ſight of God, or agreeable to God's will, or not. Every conſiderate man knows here his own <hi>Latitude,</hi> and after many a day and years laying the thing to heart, I will, if I can, tell you <hi>Mine</hi> in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>The Rule I lay down in ſubmitting to, or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any Impoſition of men, is this. <hi>We muſt ſit down and conſider what we believe to be the meaning of the Law-givers, and if we can ſubmit to it in that ſenſe or mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which we believe theirs, we muſt do it: but if we believe their ſenſe to be ſuch as we cannot take it in that ſenſe, we muſt forbear it, and ſuffer.</hi> See the Book entituled, <hi>A
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107352:4"/>Peaceable Reſolution of Conſcience touching our preſent Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> and the Margin of the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe,</hi> where that Book is cited. The bottom is this; The <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> and it is the Law-givers <hi>Meaning</hi> is his <hi>Will,</hi> which you will alſo find in them <hi>both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way here I cannot but take notice of the <hi>Seventeenth Propoſition,</hi> which is condemned in the late <hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Univerſity</hi> of <hi>Oxford, July</hi> 21. 1683. <hi>An Oath obligeth not in the ſenſe of the Impoſer, but the Takers,</hi> for which they quote and condemn the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe,</hi> when the Poſition or <hi>Rule,</hi> that all <hi>Impoſitions of our Superiours muſt be taken in the ſenſe and meaning of thoſe that Impoſe them,</hi> is the foundation of that whole <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations.</hi> Theſe expreſs words are laid down in the beginning of it, and that they may be obſerv'd, there is this Note in the Margin: <hi>To this Rule there is a double extream; The one is of thoſe who think a man muſt take every Impoſition in the ſtrict literal Conſtruction, and can ſubmit to it no otherwiſe: The other is of ſuch who ſuppoſe that if a man can frame any Interpretation of his own that is but reaſonable, he may take the words in that ſenſe, and be ſatisfied. The firſt of theſe is ſo rigid, that there is nothing to be Impoſed, but we ſhall ſtrain at it; and the laſt ſo looſe, that nothing can be Impoſed but we ſhall ſwallow it.</hi> Then is the <hi>true Medium</hi> offered there, which you have here recited before. If you ask now
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107352:4"/>farther who this <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> yet be, I will tell you. In the firſt Extream are moſt of the <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts:</hi> in the laſt are thoſe of the <hi>Conformists,</hi> which we uſed to call <hi>Latitudinarians.</hi> The name roſe up about the Uniformity Act, and this is the reaſon of it. A <hi>Latitudinarian</hi> is one that is, or was, againſt the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of indifferent things that ſtumble people, as well as the <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> but he is for the <hi>Submiſsion.</hi> And this I ſay is the reaſon becauſe of his <hi>Latitude</hi> in the <hi>Interpretation.</hi> There was an excellent perſon, eminent in Learning, and of an incomparable Temper, now with God, the Reverend Dr. <hi>Whiſcot,</hi> (the Father of this ſort of men) who was ſeveral times diſcourſing with me, and maintaining the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Opinion, being liberally ready to affirm, that a man might defend in <hi>Living</hi> with a <hi>Rational Constru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of an Impoſition by his <hi>Wit,</hi> as he might is <hi>Purſe</hi> by his <hi>Sword;</hi> but I was alwaies for holding him to the <hi>Meaning of the Law-giver.</hi> I have been ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry methinks very much, that this ſuperlative wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy man is not yet alive, that I might talk with him about this <hi>Decree</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that hath here given Judgment for me againſt him in the buſineſs, whom I would have had convinced really in Conſcience, becauſe that Opinion of his was not to be held, and I thought he did hurt others in holding it; and I do therefore heartily thank the <hi>Univerſity</hi> that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107352:5"/>have pickt up this <hi>Seventeenth Propoſition</hi> into their <hi>Decree,</hi> and condemned it, being a Tenent of ill conſequence, when <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be rendred but as ſo many <hi>Cobwebs,</hi> which may intangle a <hi>weak Judgment;</hi> but thoſe that have <hi>Wit</hi> ſhall break through them, and the Magiſtrate ſhall have no hold-faſt on any. Nevertheleſs, I thank not the Univerſity for gathering this Propoſition from the <hi>Sheriffs caſe,</hi> which profeſſeth the clean contrary as they do. And if any ſuch Tenent therefore could be deduced from any occaſional paſſage thereof <hi>by conſequence</hi> (or Logick,) ſo long as the Deſign and whole ſcope of it does bend <hi>de induſtria</hi> to the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite thereunto, <hi>ſuch a Decree as affixes to a Book that Propoſition, against which it expreſly declared, and then to burn the Book for it</hi> (if I may uſe the words of no leſs than a Biſhop who had read both the <hi>Decree</hi> and <hi>Caſe</hi>) <hi>must be very iniquitous.</hi> I put it in theſe very words, becauſe they are anothers, and he ſpake them not (I will ſuppoſe) in diſhonour to the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> but the rather becauſe he was told, it is ſome other Book they meant under the Title of the <hi>Sheriffs caſe,</hi> and not this which I ſpeak of, and own, as propoſing the ſame <hi>Doctrine</hi> which they do, and condemning the ſame <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To return, if upon mature conſideration, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Rule, I am perſuaded that the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107352:5"/>of the Parliament who impoſed the <hi>Declaration</hi> which is to be ſubſcribed by me, if I go on, was no more than I have tendred in the Explication of my former Sheets, then do I not need to be beholding to any Biſhop, who can give my ſelf the favour of <hi>ſubſcribing,</hi> and ſo require his <hi>Certificate</hi> of courſe: But if indeed (do what I can) I find my mind ſtill in ſome doubt, I muſt on neceſſity think father.</p>
            <p>It was ſome years before I could tell how to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe that <hi>Declaration</hi> at all (eſpecially as it was clogg'd till <hi>Eighty two</hi>) with any <hi>Explication.</hi> When I came to think on an <hi>Explication,</hi> it was a good while longer before I could be ſatisfied how to do it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I might put my Explication to the words of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> and ſo ſet my hand to both together. I endeavoured therefore, and made tryal, whether <hi>I</hi> might have leave to do ſo, but could not obtain it. <hi>I</hi> acknowledge the candid ingenuity, and courteous good will of the <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> but he made higher inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. I bethought my ſelf hereupon of a leſs Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that if I might by the Biſhops conſent be but permitted to write theſe words <hi>[According to a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per given into the Biſhop Iſubſcribe]</hi> in the Regiſters Book (as in the former Sheets,) it appeared to me in effect all one as to ſet my name to the words of the <hi>Declaration</hi> with my Explication, ſo long as ſuch a Paper was given in to him. I have not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107352:6"/>therefore to try again with more than one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, whether ſo little a favour as this might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and I have intimated my ſucceſs, ſo that the <hi>Condeſcenſion</hi> that a man may reaſonably expect (without a <hi>Parliament</hi>) from any <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to truſt to it, is like to come to this, <hi>to grant what the Law allows,</hi> if ſome of them will yet do that.</p>
            <p>Here are <hi>Two</hi> Steps then I have made, and the <hi>Third</hi> I am to get up. I cannot ſubſcribe <hi>without</hi> an <hi>Explication,</hi> but I can ſubſcribe <hi>with</hi> one. That was the Firſt Step. If I ſubſcribe with an Explication, it is neceſſary that <hi>I</hi> declare my Explication, but it is not neceſſary that my Explication and the words <hi>I</hi> ſubſcribe be put together in one Paper, or in the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters</hi> Book. If it be <hi>ſignified</hi> that <hi>I</hi> do it with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, it is as well, and in effect the ſame thing. This was the Second Step. If <hi>I</hi> may not <hi>ſignifie</hi> this in the Regiſters Book, <hi>I</hi> come now to conſider if <hi>I</hi> publiſh it in Print, and ſo <hi>notifie</hi> it both to <hi>Biſhop, Regiſter,</hi> and all the <hi>World,</hi> whether this really be not as well alſo, as if <hi>I</hi> were ſuffered to do ſo, and that <hi>for the ſubſtance,</hi> which will go to the heart of all my ſcruples. And if in the upſhot this will ſerve, there is none can hinder me this <hi>Laſt</hi> Step, for <hi>I</hi> land me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks here upon my <hi>right</hi> (or upon Law) when my ſtanding was but <hi>precarious</hi> before.</p>
            <p>Well! I do conſider in the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe,</hi> to what
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107352:6"/>Reſolution (or Latitude) the Author of that Paper came about the <hi>Oxford Oath.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe a man convinced that the Interpretation offered in regard to the <hi>Oath,</hi> and in regard to this <hi>Declaration</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably the very meaning of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> but he is not perſuaded beyond all doubt, and he would have ſomething for his relief in regard to that doubt. For an alleviation to this man, there is this paſſage in that <hi>Caſe. If a man is perſuaded in his Conſcience, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law-giver was no more than thus, he may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and make no ſtand; but if he believes their meaning was otherwiſe (or doubts that it was more than thus) he cannot ſwear or ſubſcribe but with limitations, and he muſt declare thoſe limitations, or forbear. But if he ſhall ſwear of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe (ſuppoſing him one that doubts) with making a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that he does it in this meaning ſuppoſing it the ſenſe of the Law-giver, and with theſe Explanatory Limitations to their meaning if in any thing indeed it be otherwiſe,</hi> if the Juſtices admit him to the <hi>Oath</hi> after this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (for whether they admit the <hi>ſenſe</hi> or not, it is no matter, becauſe they have no power in it) <hi>we are perſuaded</hi> (ſays that Paper) <hi>that his Conſcience may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſatisfaction thereby, in his compliance with the Law in theſe Impoſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the way again, from this <hi>place</hi> it is very like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Oxford Convocation</hi> might gather the <hi>Propoſition</hi> before cited out of this ſaid Book; but if ſo, I muſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107352:7"/>anſwer, Unleſs they are of the Opinion, that though a man refuſe an Oath without admittance to take it with Limitation, and then does declare his Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſo is admitted to it, he is yet obliged to perform it being taken, in the full ſenſe of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, notwithſtanding thoſe Limitations, there is no difference between <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> in this matter. But if that indeed be their Opinion, let them ſpeak it out, and make this the condemned Propoſition. <hi>An Oath taken with a declared Limitation to the ſenſe of the Impoſer, does oblige no farther than he hath declared beforehand, that he will be bound when he took it.</hi> This Propoſition I own in the behalf of the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe;</hi> if they condemn it, I crave from them ſome illumination. That an Oath in general muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ſenſe of the Impoſer, we agree, and that a man that takes it, and ſays nothing, is obliged to the full ſenſe thereof ſo taken: But if a man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his Limitations, I ſuppoſe that Inſtance alone of the Oath between <hi>Rahab</hi> and the <hi>Spies,</hi> does make the matter good on my ſide beyond diſputation. But ſure the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> can never differ with me in this, and conſequently there is ſome miſtake here about this Book. The <hi>Sheriffs caſe I</hi> ſpeak of was firſt Printed 1680. and Reprinted 1681. in one Sheet, and then again Printed the third time with the Addition of the two Papers more making
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107352:7"/>four Sheets and a half in all for the year 1682. and entituled, <hi>The Caſe of the Sheriffs, or third years Paper in regard to the Act for Corporations, being the Caſe alſo of the Diſſenting Miniſters in regard to the Act at</hi> Oxford. Whether this Paper (or Book) be the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> condemned and burnt by the <hi>Convocation, I</hi> muſt take liberty to queſtion. <hi>I</hi> do acknowledge my ſelf to be a <hi>Son</hi> of that <hi>Univerſity,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> ought not to think unmannerly of my <hi>Mother.</hi> I ought not to think ſo many not only of <hi>Perſons,</hi> but <hi>Ranks</hi> of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious perſons could be ſo <hi>overly</hi> (nay ſo directly <hi>out</hi>) in any cenſure. And why ſhould they <hi>condemn a Book</hi> that was never like to hurt any of them? Why ſhould they really <hi>burn a Book</hi> that could never have been writ for the nonce by any one of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo much to ſerve them? Why ſhould they <hi>Martyr an Innocent Book</hi> (let me ſay yet, ſeeing ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny think it <hi>this</hi>) which hath certainly offered more toward <hi>Juſtifying the Conformiſt</hi> (<hi>I</hi> pray God it may not hinder any one man from a due ſenſe of his ſin, who either went againſt his Conſcience, or knew not what he did when he Conformed), and <hi>helping the Diſſenters to Conform,</hi> than all the Books that were writ on their own ſide (which generally have waved theſe Political Points, where lay our chief ſcruples) ſince the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Uniformity? I</hi> ought not above all, to think them of ſuch a manner of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107352:8"/>at <hi>Univerſity,</hi> as if they did hate us for <hi>coming in,</hi> and yet hate us for being <hi>Nonconformiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any perſiſt that this indeed is the Book which they meant and condemn'd, <hi>I</hi> muſt not then leave that matter yet without ſome farther diſcuſſion. The <hi>Univerſity</hi> have charged the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting that an Oath <hi>obliges not in the ſenſe of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, but the Takers:</hi> The Sheriffs Caſe ſays expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>An Oath muſt be taken in the ſenſe of the Impoſer,</hi> and builds upon it. There are two queſtions therefore to be made of this. One, <hi>In what ſenſe muſt an Oath be taken?</hi> The other, <hi>In what ſenſe does it oblige being taken?</hi> If theſe be not made <hi>two,</hi> the <hi>Univerſity</hi> will he guilty of Slander, and belying the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe,</hi> which is a thing not to be imagined: But theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſtinguiſhed, it appears ſtraight that the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity</hi> and <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> agree thus far, (as was ſaid even now) that an Oath muſt be taken in the ſenſe of thoſe that Impoſe it, and when it is ſo taken, it obliges accordingly. The difficulty ariſes only when the <hi>Impoſers</hi> ſenſe and <hi>Takers</hi> do differ, and there are two Caſes herein to be propoſed, for there are no <hi>General Rules</hi> ordinarily without their <hi>Exceptions.</hi> One is the Caſe of <hi>Miſtake,</hi> when a man does honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take an Oath in that ſenſe which he believes in his Conſcience to be the very ſenſe of the <hi>Impoſer,</hi> but he comes after his taking it to underſtand the ſenſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107352:8"/>to be ſuch as he <hi>could</hi> not, and <hi>would</hi> not have taken it, if he had underſtood the ſame before: The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion then is, Whether his Oath now obliges him to the performance in that ſenſe which <hi>really</hi> is the <hi>Impoſers,</hi> or that which he <hi>underſtood</hi> to be <hi>theirs</hi> when he took it, and elſe had not taken it. If the <hi>Univerſity</hi> does hold that an Oath binds in the ſenſe of the Impoſer <hi>univerſally</hi> even in this caſe of <hi>Miſtake,</hi> and all others without diſcrimination, I deſire the Judicious to ponder well of it, whether that be a <hi>mature</hi> Determination. The other Caſe is, when a man is not miſtaken, but diſtinguiſhes the ſenſe of an Oath beforehand, and <hi>declares</hi> the ſenſe in which he takes it, <hi>excepting</hi> againſt that ſenſe wherein he <hi>cannot</hi> take it: The queſtion then ſtill ariſes, Whether the Univerſity do hold the man is obliged to the Impoſers ſenſe, notwithſtanding his Predeclaration; and if they do, I muſt leave it again to the better adviſed to conſider, whether this be a <hi>mature,</hi> or <hi>raſh</hi> Determination. If they determine the Point <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,</hi> how could they condemn the <hi>Propoſition</hi> they have condemned, without explanation or excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? In ſhort, unleſs it be another Book they mean, they have <hi>collected</hi> their Propoſition out of the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> very <hi>untowardly,</hi> and they have as <hi>overly condemned it</hi> when they have ſo done.</p>
            <p>To paſs on; It is propoſed farther in that She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107352:9"/>Caſe, that a man ſhould moreover write down his ſenſe or limitations, and give in his <hi>Writing</hi> (or that <hi>Caſe</hi> it ſelf, ſuppoſing it ſpeaks his full mind for him) to the <hi>Juſtices,</hi> together with his declaring thoſe Limitations, which if he does <hi>in abundantiorem cautelam,</hi> he is like to be ſtill the better ſatisfied: Yet if he does not, <hi>ſo long as in words, or writing, a man does but declare as openly as he ſwears</hi> (that it may be as much known,) <hi>that he takes the Oath but in ſuch or ſuch a lawful ſenſe</hi> (Sèe the Quotation in the Margin of the <hi>Caſe</hi>), this is the main there intended.</p>
            <p>There are two ways then for my ſelf here to take, to eſtabliſh me in my Reſolution. One is, if I can convince my Soul beyond doubt that the meaning of the <hi>Law-giver</hi> was no more than I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in my <hi>Explanations:</hi> And the other is, if any doubt yet remains, to heal it with the prepared Remedy.</p>
            <p>For the two firſt Clauſes of the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> they are all one (it is plain) with the two firſt Clauſes in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and it is really ſomething eaſier, in my mind, to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to the ſame things in a <hi>Declaration,</hi> than to <hi>ſwear</hi> to them in an Oath. The Contents of both Clauſes comes but to this, That it is unlawful to take Arms againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or againſt his <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> when both are certainly to be held <hi>inviolable.</hi> To <hi>take Arms</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> Clauſe muſt be conſtrued
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107352:9"/>
               <hi>Raiſing War</hi> or <hi>Forces,</hi> becauſe it is meant ſo on ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity in the <hi>second</hi> Clauſe. Nothing leſs can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by it againſt the <hi>Commiſsionated.</hi> The <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsionated</hi> are ſuch as have the <hi>Kings Authority.</hi> The Authority of the King in this Realm is <hi>Royal,</hi> not <hi>Lordly,</hi> that is, <hi>a Right to Govern according to Law.</hi> Theſe perſons conſequently who <hi>have</hi> not, or <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue</hi> not their <hi>Commiſsions</hi> according to <hi>Law,</hi> are not <hi>Commiſsionated,</hi> that is, <hi>have</hi> not, or <hi>exerciſe</hi> not <hi>his Authority.</hi> When this little Interpretation only is made, there are no Objections to be invented, but they may hereby receive a Solution. See the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin of the <hi>firſt</hi> Sheet of that <hi>Caſe.</hi> And that this is the true ſenſe of the Law-giver, let the <hi>Second</hi> and <hi>Third</hi> Sheets of the ſame be conſulted.</p>
            <p>I am not indeed ignorant of the many and hard Caſes which are, and may be raiſed here by way of Objection, and which do require therefore that I ſhould ſpeak a little fuller, though I am elſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, and this alone is as much as can be well born. The Learned and Acute Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> who like another <hi>Caleb</hi> in Divinity, does write after <hi>Fourſcore</hi> as if he were but <hi>Forty,</hi> (whether his Pen be for <hi>Fight</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> for Polemicks or Politicks) in his late Book againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſticks not to aſſert, that <hi>the Legiſlative Power</hi> in this Realm <hi>does lie ſolely in the King,</hi> and yet doth make no doubt to tell
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107352:10"/>us for all that, with others, that the Government is <hi>not Deſpotical but Political,</hi> that is, as I call it, <hi>Regal;</hi> which is thus explained by <hi>Bracton, Non eſt Rex, ubi Voluntas imperat, non Lex.</hi> As the <hi>Apostle</hi> therefore ſpeaks of his own Authority which was <hi>Spiritual,</hi> that he had none for <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> but for <hi>Edification,</hi> and that he could <hi>ſay nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth:</hi> So may we ſay of the Power of the <hi>King,</hi> which is <hi>Temporal,</hi> it is a Power <hi>according to Law,</hi> and for the Law, not <hi>againſt</hi> the Law. The <hi>King,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Officers can do nothing againſt the Law, but for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Put the Caſe then that a Prince ſhould go about to <hi>Deſtroy</hi> his whole People, which is a Caſe put by <hi>Grotius</hi> from <hi>Barclay,</hi> as inconſiſtent with <hi>Ruling</hi> them, and the Biſhop forementioned anſwers, this is not to be ſuppoſed of any man but a <hi>Mad-man.</hi> But ſuppoſe it replied, what if a Price were a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or ſo mad, or ſavage as the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who, when they had Conquered <hi>Mexico, Hiſpaniola,</hi> and thoſe places, butcher'd ſo many thouſands of them, worrying them like Beaſts with Dogs? What if a Prince were of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Duke of Alva,</hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth,</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> unto whom a hundred thouſand <hi>Hereticks</hi> were but a <hi>Breakfaſt,</hi> and he could then <hi>Dine</hi> preſently with another hundred thouſand of the ſame? Suppoſe a Prince that would <hi>alienate</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107352:10"/>his Kingdom, as King <hi>John,</hi> That would bring in the <hi>Turks</hi> upon them, or ſell them for Slaves to a Forein Tyrant? What if a Prince would raiſe an Army out of <hi>one</hi> of his Dominions that were <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and bring it into <hi>another</hi> of them that are <hi>Protestants,</hi> and ſwear that unleſs they will turn their Religion (that is, yield to be damn'd), he will burn them all, or exterminate them, according to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Council; yea, though the ſaid Religion were by Law Eſtabliſh'd? Theſe are Caſes may be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; Not that I imagine any ſuch in good earneſt ever like to be. God forbid! I am not a man of that complexion: but to the end I may make the moſt of the Objection (for I had as good elſe even quite ſay nothing), I do anatomize the Scruples of my Brethren, laying them naked before all men of equal Judgment, who may conſider whether they are <hi>with,</hi> or <hi>without</hi> Reaſon, and ſearching the wound to the quick; I am willing ſo to apply the <hi>Remedy,</hi> as at once to procure both the Adverſaries <hi>Compaſsion,</hi> and our own <hi>Satisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe then it be demanded whether a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> or <hi>whole Nation</hi> have a right by the law of Nature to defend themſelves in theſe Caſes, though <hi>Particular Perſons</hi> have not? I muſt anſwer, that ſuch Caſes as theſe are ſo odious in the naming, as we are not to conceive they came once into the mind
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107352:11"/>of the <hi>Law-giver</hi> (that is, the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> as one <hi>Corporation</hi>) who impoſed this <hi>Declaration:</hi> and conſequently that they are not to be put, for the ſtumbling ſuch as are to ſubſcribe it: but if they be ſuppoſed and put, that it was the mind of the Impoſers they ſhould be excepted, or excluded by ſuch an Interpretation of the <hi>Commiſsionated,</hi> as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given.</p>
            <p>For, for inſtance but in one Caſe more that is caſie and obvious: Suppoſe a Prince of our Land ſhould ſend perſons for the Levying Money on the Subject without a Parliament, or Parliament-Tax: I doubt not but the <hi>Conſtables, Juſtices,</hi> or <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> might keep the Peace in the name of the <hi>King</hi> againſt theſe men: and that yet we may maintain it unlawful to <hi>take Arms againſt thoſe that are Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionated by him,</hi> becauſe ſuch as theſe (I have ſaid) are not <hi>Commiſsionated,</hi> or ſuch Commiſſions have no <hi>Authority,</hi> and are no Commiſſions. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of our Kingdom is ſuch, as the King can Commiſſion no ſuch thing. And when I have ſaid ſo in regard to this one Caſe which is the <hi>lower,</hi> the ſame Anſwer may be given to thoſe Caſes, which are <hi>higher,</hi> I account beyond diſputation.</p>
            <p>The Learned <hi>Arniſaeus</hi> writes a Book (I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) on this Subject, <hi>Non licere ſubditis ulla ex cauſa contra legitimum Principem arma ſumere.</hi> He holds the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107352:11"/>Poſition indefinitely in the affirmative, yet makes no ſcruple upon ſuppoſition of any ſuch a Caſe, to put in his Limitations: And why may we not conceive that when a Parliament impos'd upon us ſuch a <hi>Declaration</hi> as this, they did intend we ſhould ſubſcribe it no otherwiſe but in ſuch a <hi>Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as the Learned who have moſt Loyally written for Monarchy, and againſt Rebellion, do maintain <hi>ſuch a Poſition;</hi> that is, <hi>prout prudens definierit?</hi> The <hi>Commiſsionated</hi> (I ſay) are ſuch as have the Kings Authority. The Kings Authority is <hi>Political,</hi> and he can <hi>give</hi> no other, but what he <hi>hath</hi> himſelf, to any. If his Authority then be <hi>for</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> and he has none <hi>againſt</hi> it; and if it be againſt the <hi>King</hi> only, and thoſe <hi>Commiſsionated</hi> by him, that is, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and his <hi>Authority</hi> only, that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it unlawful to take Arms, I ſee not any thing left in the Objection (let what Caſe ſoever be put) but that this <hi>Declaration</hi> in the <hi>Two firſt Clauſes</hi> of it may be ſubſcribed.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>laſt</hi> Clauſe, [<hi>And I will Conform to the Lyturgy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>as it is now by Law Eſtabliſhed</hi>] let us compare it with the laſt Clauſe of the Oath, <hi>[And I will not at any time endeavour any Alteration of Government in Church or State]</hi> and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly methinks a mans heart will begin to beat much rather at his approach to the <hi>taking</hi> the <hi>latter,</hi> than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107352:12"/>
               <hi>ſubſcribing</hi> the <hi>former.</hi> But there is one thing inſtead of all to ſatisfie. This Subſcription is not impoſed only on <hi>Miniſters;</hi> but on ſuch as <hi>Teach School,</hi> and <hi>Tutors at Univerſity;</hi> and it cannot be conceived the meaning of the Law-giver, that <hi>ſuch perſons</hi> in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing this <hi>Declaration,</hi> ſhould be engaged to <hi>read</hi> Common-Prayer, but to <hi>hear it,</hi> or <hi>go to Church,</hi> or Chappel: Now, while I am a Miniſter without any Place which requires my reading Common-Prayer, I am to be underſtood to engage no farther in my <hi>Conforming to the Lyturgy,</hi> that ſuch who are bound to ſubſcribe, and are no Miniſters (For if I took a <hi>Living,</hi> I muſt ſubſcribe this <hi>Declaration</hi> again, which I ſhould not ſcruple to do in my former Sheets <hi>Explication,</hi> but in my ſtate, that have no place to officiate in, and ſeek none, I ſuppoſe that in the mind of the <hi>Law-giver</hi> I am not yet bound ſo far): and as for going to Church, it is what I am wont to do, without <hi>Subſcription.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is there any word in this <hi>Subſcription</hi> that confines the Subſcriber <hi>ſo</hi> to go to <hi>Church,</hi> as that he may never go to other <hi>Meetings</hi> upon any occaſion. It were exceſſively rigorous to ſtretch the words ſo far, and there is not one of a hundred that would rationally gather that this was the <hi>Parliaments</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this <hi>Subſcription.</hi> If it were, I declare my Exception.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107352:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> muſt moreover ſignifie, that in Subſcribing, <hi>I will Conform to the Lyturgy, I</hi> do not oblige my ſelf to every thing whatſoever that is enjoyned in that Book, as <hi>I</hi> do in general to go to Divine Service in the Pariſh Congregation. More particularly, in the Preface before the Prayers it is required of all Miniſters, that they <hi>ſay daily the Morning and Evening Prayer either privately or openly, not being let by ſickneſs, or ſome urgent Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> do not apprehend that by <hi>Conforming to the Lyturgy,</hi> it was the Law-givers meaning I ſhould be engaged to this, who do not, and will not engage my ſelf to that which I ſhall never perform, for I ſhall uſe my <hi>own</hi> Prayers at home. Indeed I think that what Miniſter ſoever does make the Declaration of <hi>aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained in, and preſcribed by that Book,</hi> he muſt be according to the <hi>Law-givers</hi> meaning en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged hereunto, for he does conſent to <hi>all</hi> in regard to the <hi>Uſe:</hi> And I ſhall not lightly therefore ever (I think) make that Declaration, in <hi>thoſe words and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, if the ſenſe of <hi>this Clauſe</hi> comes to no more in my ſtate than going to Church, and of the <hi>other two</hi> to no more than <hi>I</hi> have delivered, then may <hi>I</hi> very ſafely yield to <hi>this ſubſcription,</hi> and if I am to do <hi>what I can,</hi> both in regard to the <hi>fifth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and in regard to the <hi>uniting</hi> and ſtrengthning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107352:13"/>the <hi>Proteſtant intereſt,</hi> and in regard to the <hi>uſe of my Miniſtry</hi> (I charge my brethren by the way to lay theſe three things with me well to heart, for real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſtick greatly for want of their company) or at leaſt the <hi>freer uſe of it, to preach in publick,</hi> then is it not only <hi>lawful,</hi> but what it ſeems I am <hi>bound</hi> to do. Nevertheleſs becauſe I am not certain, or at leaſt not ſo certainly perſwaded of the mind of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> as to be in regard to <hi>all particulars</hi> beyond doubt, and becauſe I ſhall be apt to be raiſing ſcruples after, I muſt for the preventing my trouble, and ſecuring my peace, fly to that refuge in regard to this <hi>Declaration,</hi> which is ſet open in regard to the <hi>Oath</hi> in the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe:</hi> And I do therefore make this preſent &amp; publick declaration (I crave pardon for the neceſſary repetition) that <hi>in this meaning,</hi> which I have all along delivered, <hi>ſuppoſing it the meaning of the Law-giver, and with theſe explanatory limitations to the meaning, if in any thing indeed it be otherwiſe,</hi> I do ſubſcribe the <hi>Declaration</hi> required to be ſubſcribed in the <hi>Act for Uniformity,</hi> whenſoever I ſet my hand to the <hi>Biſhops Regiſters</hi> book; whom <hi>I</hi> deſire by theſe preſents with all other any way concerned, to take cognizance of it. And alſo when <hi>I</hi> give my <hi>aſſent</hi> to the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> (if I give it) <hi>I</hi> do <hi>aſſent</hi> with my Firſt ſheets foreprized <hi>explication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> know there is no body of a deliberate under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107352:13"/>but he does and muſt make ſome Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the <hi>Articles</hi> (to ſpeak alſo a little of theſe) in which he conceives them true, or elſe he cannot aſſent to them according to <hi>his Conſcience,</hi> let it be as large as it will, if he hath <hi>any</hi> at all: But <hi>I</hi> muſt profeſs this is not ſatisfactory to <hi>mine</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a declaration alſo of the ſenſe of ſuch of them (which you may ſee in my former ſheets) as <hi>I</hi> do ſcruple. <hi>I</hi> will as honeſtly give my reaſon, and it is, becauſe if I aſſent to the Articles and ſay nothing, my Conſcience tells me <hi>I</hi> muſt <hi>Interpretatively</hi> be thought to aſſent to them in the ſenſe of the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, that is (as <hi>I</hi> have been uſed to think) of the Majority of the <hi>Convocation</hi> that framed and decreed them, and <hi>I</hi> do verily believe <hi>their</hi> ſenſe to be ſuch in ſome of them, as <hi>I</hi> do certainly in my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment diſſent from it. <hi>I</hi> might inſtance in the 18th and the 11th Article, but <hi>I</hi> refer to my <hi>Two</hi> firſt <hi>Steps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be ſaid, it is true it was the <hi>Convocation</hi> decreed the Articles, but it is the <hi>King</hi> that <hi>rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies</hi> them, and when the ratification is from his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority alone, it is he, is the ſole <hi>Impoſer. I</hi> anſwer, this is a notion but newly riſen up in my mind, and if it prove right after due canvaſſing, then muſt we look into the Declaration of the King (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>James</hi> or <hi>Charles,</hi> or both) which is ſet before the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107352:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Articles, to find out what that <hi>ſenſe</hi> is which is there <hi>ratified,</hi> and we have theſe words. <hi>We will that no man put his own comment to be the meaning of the Article, but ſhall take it in the literal and grammatical ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> muſt ask here in the firſt place, what was the intent of the King when he ſaies he will have no man put his own comment on the Article? Can any man indeed ſubſcribe the Article and not make his own Interpretation? This were not to ſubſcribe with Truth or Judgment; on on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he muſt not make <hi>his ſenſe to be the meaning,</hi> that is, his private ſenſe to go for the ſole publick Interpretation. There is a latitude manifeſtly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and allowed by the King in this <hi>literal and grammatical ſenſe,</hi> becauſe it is ſuppoſed by him that all the <hi>Clergy</hi> though of different Judgments do ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe them, and every one pleads them in favour of his own opinion. I muſt ask them next, whether this <hi>literal and grammatical ſenſe</hi> be to be underſtood <hi>with</hi> reference to the <hi>mind</hi> of the <hi>Convocation</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed theſe Articles, or <hi>without</hi> any regard to it? All <hi>words</hi> (we know) are nothing but the ſignification of the <hi>mind,</hi> that mind muſt be ſome bodies, and an Article having no mind, but they that paſſed them, I ſhould judge that the literal and grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe of an Article is the meaning or mind of thoſe that decreed it, Interpreted or Underſtood
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107352:14"/>by a Literal and Grammatical conſtruction of the words wherein they have expreſſed that mind or meaning: But if the Literal and Grammatical ſenſe which is authorized by the King's Declaration, be underſtood without any ſuch reference, ſo that a man may frame for himſelf any ſenſe he can, ſo long as he makes it hold true in a Literal, Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſenſe, then muſt I confeſs here a great freedom, eaſe, and kind of deliverance appearing to me for my Aſſenting to ſome of the Articles which have moſt ſtumbled me, becauſe in the ſenſe of thoſe that decreed them I could not do it (I will name particularly the 18th and 36th Article): Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, in regard that there is, or may be, ſome other of theſe Articles as hard to be ſubſcribed in the <hi>Literal and Grammatical ſenſe,</hi> as thoſe two to me foreintimated in the ſenſe of the <hi>Convocation,</hi> I do find my ſelf ſtill conſtrained to keep to my forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Declaration. That is, if I take the liberty (I ſay) of an <hi>Explication,</hi> and <hi>Declare</hi> the ſame, the Biſhop and all the World do ſee how I aſſent to them, which is, in a <hi>Doctrinal Interpretation,</hi> and with which I am then methinks well ſatisfied: But if I make no Explication, or if I uſe no words about it, I muſt be conſtrued to aſſent to them in the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Interpretation;</hi> and whether that be the ſtrict <hi>Literal and Grammatical ſenſe,</hi> authenticated by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107352:15"/>
               <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>ſenſe</hi> in which they were at firſt <hi>decreed</hi> or <hi>paſſed,</hi> it will come all to one, <hi>I</hi> have no way without the courſe <hi>I</hi> take, to eſcape prevarication. This is my Conſcience, and <hi>I</hi> go by it.</p>
            <p>To return to the Subſcription, it may be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, in the end whether it be lawful to <hi>Subſcribe</hi> a <hi>Declaration</hi> or <hi>Swear</hi> an <hi>Oath</hi> with an <hi>Explication,</hi> if it be ſuch as includes any reſtriction or limitation to the ſenſe of the Impoſer. For Anſwer therefore to this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> do premiſe that if any man <hi>Subſcribe</hi> or <hi>Swear</hi> to an <hi>Impoſition,</hi> without making any Declaration about it, he muſt frame no Interpretation in his mind but that which he believes to be the very meaning of the Law-giver, or elſe he prevaricates, or equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates (his mind and words being not equal), which is to ſin againſt Truth: But if he does <hi>declare</hi> himſelf before he <hi>Swears</hi> or <hi>Subſcribes,</hi> I take that to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>fair dealing,</hi> and <hi>another</hi> matter. Only I muſt yet make a difference between a mans <hi>declaring</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>upon Conviction</hi> that the ſenſe of the Impoſer is ill, and ſuch as he cannot Subſcribe but by vertue of that Declaration: And his declaring <hi>upon doubt only,</hi> that is, being perſuaded as to the main, that the ſenſe of the Impoſer is no other but what is good, or what he can Subſcribe, and yet there remains ſome doubt retarding him. In the <hi>one</hi> caſe <hi>I</hi> think there is more reaſon for a man to put the queſtion,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107352:15"/>which yet I ſhall ſpeak to by and by: When in the <hi>other</hi> I think the <hi>declaring a mans ſelf</hi> is a Salve ſo <hi>proper</hi> to the Malady, and ſo <hi>innocent,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> ſhould be ſorry if any queſtion at all be made of the <hi>Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of it. For the Truth is, <hi>I</hi> do account the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of this Caſe in regard to the frequency of it, ſo needful, that if there were nothing elſe in the <hi>Sheriffs Caſe</hi> beſides that, it were fit to be Printed for <hi>its</hi> ſake. This being premiſed, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer directly.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If there be any evil in this, it muſt be either in regard to the <hi>Fifth</hi> Commandment, or the <hi>Ninth.</hi> Either becauſe it is againſt our duty of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Higher Powers, or againſt our <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> or <hi>Truth.</hi> Here is no ſin againſt Truth and Sincerity, for therefore do I make my <hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that I may not forſake <hi>Truth,</hi> but keep my <hi>Sincerity</hi> in what I do: And here is no ſin of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,</hi> becauſe the Law of <hi>God</hi> ſuperſedes that of <hi>Man;</hi> and when I do <hi>what I can</hi> in regard to the <hi>one,</hi> I muſt do <hi>no more</hi> (and I think <hi>declare</hi> it) by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If a Poſition be capable (note <hi>I</hi> ſay capable, not if uncapable) of a <hi>good</hi> ſenſe, and a <hi>bad,</hi> and the bad ſenſe were the ſenſe of the <hi>Impoſer,</hi> and yet <hi>I</hi> ſubſcribe it in the <hi>good</hi> ſenſe with profeſſing my <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt the <hi>bad,</hi> and that be as well
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107352:16"/>known, as that <hi>I</hi> have ſubſcribed, <hi>I</hi> do not ſin thereby againſt <hi>Truth,</hi> becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſubſcribe not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in this caſe to the <hi>Poſition</hi> of the <hi>Impoſer,</hi> but to <hi>another</hi> which I can ſubſcribe. You may ſay, Here is a Cheat then put upon the <hi>Law.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>no Cheat,</hi> which ſignifies ſomething <hi>diſhoneſt,</hi> but an <hi>honeſt Avoidance</hi> of it, or lawful ſhift (without equivocation, mental reſervation, or Jeſuitical Trick), which all that do not ſubmit to it, do uſe in ſome other way as they can, without ſin. Indeed, if he that is to take my Subſcription, or my Oath, will, after I have made my Declaration, refuſe me upon that account ſaying, <hi>This is not the Oath Impoſed, and I cannot accept it</hi>), he may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent my paſſing, but if he does not, (and will let me go off with <hi>another,</hi> which ſerves as well, or better), <hi>I</hi> ſee no evil in it by him or me, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſtill no detriment to the Publick in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If you ask then how ſhall a <hi>Certificate</hi> be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me that I have <hi>ſubſcribed,</hi> I muſt confeſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I may write <hi>According to a Paper delivered in to the Biſhop I ſubſcribe,</hi> and ſo it be certified like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>According to a Paper delivered in he hath ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,</hi> I ſee not how a <hi>Certificate</hi> ſhould be <hi>other</hi> in this caſe.</p>
            <p>But 3. I thank God this is not the caſe here in good earneſt, for the <hi>Explication</hi> which I do give
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107352:16"/>of this <hi>Subſcription,</hi> and in which (as reſpecting me): it may be clearly ſubſcribed, is the very, ſenſe it ſelf (I ſuppoſe) of the <hi>Low-giver,</hi> inſomuch as <hi>I</hi> think therefore <hi>I ſhould</hi> my ſelf ſcruple no farther, and that another in my ſtead <hi>would</hi> not, and <hi>need</hi> not: Only being conſcious of ſome former wound on my mind, <hi>I</hi> am forced to provide againſt my own infirmity. And the truth is, it is in <hi>this caſe</hi> alone I dare inſiſt ſo much on what <hi>I</hi> do, referring the <hi>other caſe</hi> before to the Judgment of the more aſſured, and to my own farther conſideration: When if an Impoſition (I ſay) be indeed ſuch as that the ſenſe thereof is really doubtful, or I indeed doubt of the Law-givers meaning therein (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if in my belief I en cline more to think the <hi>good</hi> ſenſe <hi>theirs</hi> rather than the <hi>evil</hi>) I cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any means more <hi>honeſt,</hi> or ſo <hi>proper,</hi> as ſuch a <hi>Declaration of ones ſelf</hi> mentioned for the keeping a good Conſcience (or rather for ſatisfying the ſame) in what a man does. And now if the Biſhop then herein, and all good men <hi>will,</hi> or <hi>do,</hi> bear with me, I do them no hurt, and they relieve me. <hi>Bear ye one anothers burdens</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle), <hi>and ſo fulfil the Law of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remains only, that I go to ſome Bishop after I have Printed my Paper, and give it him. If when he hath read it, he thinks <hi>my Explanations</hi> (or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107352:17"/>ſenſe) agreeable to the <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> he can have nothing to ſay againſt me: if he think otherwiſe, let him chuſe whether he will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me. I am not to be ſollicitous about his thoughts, ſo long as I have diſcharged my ſelf. He cannot refuſe me in <hi>Law,</hi> and I in <hi>my Conſcience</hi> have my ſatisfaction. Let him but read my Papers, or let me (or his Chaplain) ſignifie the Contents to him, and all is brought to this Period.</p>
            <p>Before my going off, that I may underſtand my ſelf, and be underſtood, there are Two things I am to make my Application for, to the Biſhop, or Biſhops; For a <hi>Certificate;</hi> For a <hi>Licence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Certificate, That</hi> is to be granted of courſe upon my ſubſcribing the Declaration requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Uniformity Act.</hi> In order to ſubſcribe it, I made in my former Sheets Two Steps. The <hi>Firſt</hi> was, I deſired liberty to <hi>explain the Declaration, and then to ſet my hand to it in the ſame Paper with my Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi> This being not granted, and the way of <hi>Subſcribing</hi> (as I am informed) being by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters</hi> inſerting that <hi>Declaration</hi> in his <hi>Book,</hi> and the Miniſters putting their Names only to it, my <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> Step or Requeſt hath been that I may do ſo with the liberty of writing theſe words, <hi>According to a Paper delivered in to the Biſhop, I ſubſcribe.</hi> What hurt it could be to any Biſhop, for me to ſubſcribe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107352:17"/>thus, that is, with theſe words in his Regiſters Book, I-am ignorant, either from the <hi>Law,</hi> or from the <hi>Canons:</hi> But becauſe I am apprehenſive how apt the Biſhops themſelves are to ſuſpect it as dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, or though <hi>ſafe,</hi> not to allow it, becauſe <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, I</hi> am put upon a procedure to a <hi>Third</hi> Step in theſe ſecond preſent Sheets, which is, <hi>the capacitating my ſelf againſt the need of more Condeſcenſion than the Law allows, if no other can be had;</hi> and this hath not been altogether unprepared before in my thoughts. It is no ſin for a Biſhop to read my Sheets, if <hi>I</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to him, no breach of the Law, or of the Cannons. If he do read them, or hath read them, and <hi>I</hi> know that, <hi>I</hi> am free then to ſeek to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. If he will not read my Paper, or hear the Contents, then will not <hi>I</hi> neither <hi>ſubſcribe;</hi> If he will, or hath, and would not after admit me upon that account, <hi>I</hi> ſhall acquieſce in his pleaſure; but ſo long as <hi>I</hi> offer to ſubſcribe as other do, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not refuſe me an Admiſſion, nor a <hi>Certificate,</hi> becauſe the Act of Parliament does require it.</p>
            <p>For a <hi>Licence then to Preach,</hi> the matter <hi>I</hi> confeſs is not altogether the ſame. <hi>Here</hi> is a <hi>May, there</hi> was a <hi>Muſt.</hi> In the Biſhops granting <hi>Licences,</hi> they go ordinarily upon the <hi>Canons,</hi> and the 36th Canon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires Three Points or Articles to be ſubſcribed, with an <hi>Ego libenter &amp; ex animo ſubſcriboſ:</hi> Upon thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107352:18"/>terms <hi>I</hi> ſeek not a Licence, (<hi>I</hi> cannot, <hi>I</hi> never ſhall believe) but upon the <hi>Act for Uniformity,</hi> where we may find theſe words. <hi>And be it further Enacted, That no Perſon ſhall be allowed to Preach, &amp;c. unleſs he be Licenſed by the Archbiſhop, or Biſhop, and ſhall in the preſence of the ſame Archbiſhop, or Biſhop, read the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles of Religion, with a Declaration of his unfeigned Aſſent to the ſame.</hi> By which words it appear that though the <hi>Canons</hi> require <hi>Two</hi> Points more than Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to the 39 Articles, a Biſhop (at leaſt the Archbiſhop) may juſtifie himſelf by this <hi>Act,</hi> if he require but that <hi>one,</hi> that is, if he give me a Licence only upon my <hi>Reading in his preſence,</hi> and declaring my Aſſent to the 39 <hi>Articles of Religion.</hi> And why am I to <hi>Read</hi> the Articles <hi>in his preſence,</hi> but that it is to be ſuppoſed the mind of the <hi>Law-giver,</hi> that he may examine me thereupon, if he will, whether I underſtand them, or how? And if ſo, I muſt on neceſſity explain my ſelf, and conſequently it is ſo far from being againſt <hi>Law</hi> to accept of my Aſſent <hi>with</hi> an <hi>Explication,</hi> that it ſeems rather the intent of the Law-giver that it ſhould not be taken <hi>without.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note moreover, To come for a Licence upon a man's being Beneficed in a Dioceſs is <hi>one</hi> thing, and to ſeek a Licence for Occaſional Sermons is <hi>another.</hi> The Canon does impoſe its Subſcription upon all that have any Living, Lecture, or Preferment in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107352:18"/>Church, but for a liberty to Preach meerly on occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without any Publick Emolument, I think no more needs be required than what is made neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Uniformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Canons be conſulted, the Biſhops will find this true, that if the ſhall give a Licenſe for Preaching to any that have Benefice, <hi>Living</hi> or <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> in their <hi>Dioceſs,</hi> without requiring of him the Canonical Subſcription, they are obnoxious to a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty; but what is it? why ſuch a Biſhop ſhall be ſuſpended for a year from doing ſo any more, That is in effect all, and how rarely was that penalty it ſelf ever executed upon any? But if he give a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence only for Occaſional Preaching, where a man hath no Dignity, Living, or Lecture in the Dioceſs, let the Order of the Canons be inſpected, they will find no penalty inflictable for that. And if there be no penalty to be found in ſuch a caſe, <hi>quod impunè fieri poteſt,</hi> I muſt urge, <hi>id lieet;</hi> and the <hi>Licet</hi> then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, there can be no queſtion remain but upon the <hi>Libet</hi> only.</p>
            <p>And now whether the Biſhop or Biſhops will deal with me, as he may, according only to the <hi>Act,</hi> or will ſtand with me upon the <hi>Canons,</hi> which he may chuſe, the Lord knows. I have reaſon to doubt. If my Requeſt be grated, it is well; I will ſay of it as <hi>Lot</hi> ſaid of <hi>Zoar, It is a little one,</hi> and my Miniſtry
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107352:19"/>
               <hi>ſhall live;</hi> let them but <hi>read</hi> my Papers, and <hi>admit</hi> me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ask no more. But if they will not grant it, I have done; for when I have gone ſo far as <hi>I can, I</hi> will not be got to make a Step farther to what <hi>I cannot</hi> for any thing, or any body (through Gods grace) in the world.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs moreover, that I am my ſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding timerous, and backward to the doing any thing in order to <hi>Miniſterial</hi> Conformity, although I am for coming to Church as a <hi>Pariſhioner,</hi> even more forwards than other; for it hath ſtill been my pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and I have been engag'd in my Opinion and Books againſt Separation. My <hi>fears</hi> about doing this are ſecret and dark, and whether it be <hi>Superſtition</hi> only; or <hi>aliquid</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſome <hi>Impreſs</hi> from God, it is for ought I ſee unevitable; ſo that I am not ſure if the Biſhops at laſt would let me, whether <hi>that</hi> will. I do not uſe here any <hi>Colour</hi> (God is my witneſs), but I ſpeak with a <hi>feeling care</hi> as <hi>I</hi> would of my <hi>Life:</hi> &amp; I muſt therefore conclude thus. As on the part of the Biſhops, <hi>If they will;</hi> So on my part alſo, if it be <hi>right,</hi> if it be <hi>meet,</hi> if I be <hi>clear</hi> in my Soul if <hi>I can</hi> do it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN HUMFREY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107352:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
